<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <excerpt work="To The Lighthouse" author="Virginia Woolf" source="http://www.woolfonline.com">
        <title>TIME PASSES</title>
        <chapter n="1">
            <head>I</head>
            <p n="1">
                <s n="1">It grew darker.</s>
                <s n="2">Clouds covered the moon; in the early hours of the morning a thin rain
                    drummed on the roof, and starlight and moonlight and all light on sky and earth
                    was quenched.</s>
                <s n="3">Nothing could survive the flood, the profusion, the downpouring of the
                    immense darkness which, creeping in at keyholes and crevices, stole round the
                    window blinds, came in to the bedrooms, and swallowed up, here a jug and basin,
                    there a bowl of red and yellow dahlias, there the sharp edges and firm bulk of a
                    chest of drawers.</s>
                <s n="4">Not only was furniture confounded; but there was scarcely anything left of
                    body or mind by which one could say &apos;this is he&apos; or &apos;this is
                    she&apos;; but from the many bodies lying asleep either in the rigid attitudes
                    of the old passively creased in the creases of the beds, or easily lying
                    scarcely covered, in childhood, as if a cloud lightly curved under them, there
                    rose, to break silvery on the surface, thoughts, dreams, impulses, of which the
                    sleepers by day knew nothing.</s>
                <s n="5">Now a hand was raised as if to clutch something or perhaps ward off
                    something; now the anguish which is forbidden to cry out for comfort parted the
                    lips of the sleepers; now and then somebody laughed out loud, as if sharing a
                    joke with nothingness.</s>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
                <s n="6">It seemed almost as if there must be ghostly confidantes about, sharers,
                    comforters, who, stooping by the bedside, gravely treasured up and engulphed in
                    the folds of their cloaks, in their compassionate hearts, what was murmured and
                    cried, accepted and understood those changes from torture to calm, from hate to
                    indifference, which came and went and came again upon the sleeper&apos;s
                    faces.</s>
                <s n="7">It seemed, at least, as if each reached out and found standing at the foot
                    of his bed the counterpart of his thoughts, the sharer of his deeds, found in
                    sleep a completeness denied him by day, and to that cried and to that confided
                    and laughed the senseless wild laughter which, had the waking heard it, would
                    have startled them.</s>
                <s n="8">To each a sharer, to each thought an answer, and in this knowledge content
                    - it might be so.</s>
                <s n="9">It might be that dreaming and sleeping each put off the cumber and trouble
                    of flesh and left the house and paced the beach and asked of the wave and the
                    sky: is the sharp-edged furniture all, and the flowers; is the day all; is our
                    duty to the day?</s>
            </p>
            <p>
                <s n="10">The waves breaking seemed like night shaking her head back and letting
                    despairingly her dark down, and musing and mourning as if she lamented the doom
                    which drowned the earth and extinguished its lights and of all ships and towns
                    left nothing.</s>
            </p>
        </chapter>
    </excerpt>
</xml>
